ANS Record Group 3: Development and Membership
ANS Archives
- Series: General photographs, 1868-ongoing; 10 cubic feet (23 boxes)
  - Box 18 of 23: 2005-2007
    - Annual Dinner Gala in honor of Mr. Q. David Bowers (portfolio with compact disc), January 12, 2006
    - Archer Huntington Award & Margaret Thompson Memorial Lecture to Dr. Michel Amandry
    - Krause-Mishler Forum, “The Story of Swedish Money from 1523 to 2006” by Ian Wisehn (portfolio with compact disc), October 12, 2006
    - Harry W. Fowler Memorial Lecture, “The Athenian Empire and the Spartan Coinage Decree,” Andrew Meadows and the presentation of the book, Agoranomia, offered to John Kroll on his retirement (portfolio with compact disc), October 20, 2006
    - Archer M. Huntington Award and Margaret Thompson Memorial Lecture, “Counterfeiting in Colonial and Pre-Federal America,” Dr. Philip Mossman, (portfolio with compact disc), November 10, 2006
    - COAC, “Newby’s St. Patrick Coinage” (portfolio with compact disc), November 11, 2006
    - One Hundred and Forty Ninth Annual Meeting (portfolio with compact disc), October 21, 2006
    - Gala 2007, in honor of Chester L. Krause (portfolio with compact disc), January 11, 2007
    - American Numismatic Society Recording and Preserving the Past, Dr. Roger Bland on “How British Fair Play Has United the Public” and “Not Just a Pretty Face,” by Shailendra Bhandare (portfolio with compact disc), July 11, 2007
    - One Hundred and Fiftieth Annual Meeting (portfolio with compact disc), October 20, 2007
  - Box 19 of 23: 2008-
    - Opening of 1H2—Varick Street (portfolio with compact disc), October 24, 2008
    - Lecture: Beauty and Sublimity: Why Greek Coins are so Admired (portfolio with compact disc), November 11, 2008
    - Lecture: The Thirty Pieces of Silver-A Modern Numismatic Perspective, November 19, 2008
    - Annual Dinner Gala in Honor of Harvey G. Stack (portfolio with compact disc), January 8, 2009
    - 2009 Saltus Award, Lecture on the sculpture of Andrea Riccio
  - Box 20 of 23: Miscellaneous coins and medals
    Photographs of various coins and medals used for exhibits and publications.
  - Box 21 of 23: Oversized and special
    - Portrait of Daniel Parish, Jr.
    - Portrait of Lyman Low
    - Portrait of Frank Higgins
    - Audubon Terrace construction, 1929-1930
    - Humorous photograph from Robert I. Nesmith to Sawyer McA. Mosser, October 28, 1944
    - Glass plate negative: Joan Fagerlie, Copenhagen Coin Cabinet, September-November, 1958
  - Box 22 of 23: Oversized
    - Portrait of John Reilly, Jr.
    - Portrait of Henry Chapman
    - Banquet: Members of the N.Y. Numismatic Club at Keen’s Chophouse, used in Adelson’s book, p. 156-7
    - Banquet: Given by Thomas Elder for buyers at an auction sale
    - Banquet: Tri-State Coin & Stamp Convention, Jamestown, New York, June 17-18, 1932
    - Banquet: Westchester County Coin Club, Second Anniversary Dinner, Roger Smith Hotel, White Plains, New York, April 16, 1936
    - Brooklyn Coin Club, Fifth Annual Dinner, Joe’s Restaurant, Brooklyn, January 5, 1937
    - Banquet: 8th Annual Convention Banquet, Numismatic Association of Southern California, Statler Hilton Hotel, Los Angeles, California, February 2, 1963
    - Banquet: Unidentified
    - Group photograph in front of building – Includes John Reilly Jr. and Edward Newell
    - Group photograph: Henry Chapman sale of the Andrew Zabriskie collection, June, 1909 (framed)
    - Group photograph: Auction Sale Collection of Coins of George H. Earle Jr., Catalogued by Henry Chapman, Philadelphia, June 25, 26, 27, (28), 29, 1912 (copy)
    - Group photograph: Sale of the Lyman Collection, Office of S.H. Chapman, November 7, 1913 (copy)
    - Portrait of Russian violinist Joseph Piastro Borissoff, signed “To my dearest and best friend Fannie and Emmanuel Dobrowsky” (framed), 1923
  - Box 23 of 23: Oversized
    - Drawing of fence for the American Numismatic Society, S.W. Morgan, Architect, October 25, 1955
    - Agnes Baldwin Brett portrait
    - Audubon Terrace, including Eidlitz addition (1929-1930), West Hall interior (1930), and Broadway entrance (1940s or 1950s)
    - New York Academy of Medicine building—Used in Adelson book
    - Hispanic Society of America (HSA) building—Used in Adelson book, 1905
    - Edward Groh portraits
    - Louis West portrait
    - Michael Bates with coin tray in vault (on board)
    - Frank Campbell in the Library at Audubon Terrace, includes Edward Janis (on board)
    - Alan Stahl and William Warden examining coins (on board)
    - Plaque with photograph of William Herbert Sheldon
- Series: Publication acknowledgments, 1878-1908; 0.5 cubic feet (2 boxes)
  Letters and completed forms from persons, historical societies, and other associations acknowledging receipt of ANS publications such as proceedings, circulars, printed lectures, and the Society’s constitution and bylaws. Most are perfunctory, though some touch on other matters. A letter (1884) from William Legett Bramhall, one of the Society’s first members (joined November 3, 1858), discusses his desire to start a numismatic society in Washington D.C. and mentions his remaining coin collection housed in three walnut cases obtained from Joseph Levick. Edward Cogan refers to “the [David] Proskey disgraceful fair,” adding, “he deserves to be exposed” (1878).
  Correspondence; Bramhall, William J.; Cogan, Edward D., 1803-1884; Acknowledgments
  Open to all researchers.
- Series: Membership surveys, 1889-1897, 1995, 2002; 1.5 cubic feet (2 boxes)
  Questionnaires
  Contains questionnaires completed by members on the question of changing the location of the Society’s meetings and efforts to increase the rolls of resident members (1889), completed and blank “circular to members” forms which sought biographical information from members to be used in the event of the member’s death (ca. 1897), forms completed by members in response to a request for information to be used in a new ANS database (1995) and the final draft, compilation of comments, and returned and completed forms from a survey sent to members 2002. The surveys from the 1890s contain a wealth of biographical details. Those from 1995 mostly just provide directory information. The surveys of 2002 mainly gauge use, opinions, and demographics.
  Individuals who completed “circular to members” questionnaires (ca. 1897) are: Adams, William; Alexander, Robert C.; Andrews, Frank D.; Arnold, George C.; Atwood, Daniel T.; Attinelli, Emmanuel J.; Bailey, James M.; Barrington, Rachel T.; Barron, Edward J.; Belden, Bauman L.; Bellas, Henry H.; Benson, Frank S.; Bolen, John A; Boucher, Adelard J.; Bramhall, William L.; Brenner, Victor D; Burchard, Horatio C.; Burtsell, Richard L.; Chenoweth, Alexander C.; Colburn, Jeremiah; Darling, Charles W.; Deats, Hiram E.; de Morgan, Henri; Doughty, Francis W.; Dreier, Johann C. L.; Drowne, Henry R.; Dudley, James F.; Ely, Foster; Ely, Herman; Fewsmith, William; French, William M.P.; Frossard, Edouard; Gasten, William; Goddard, William C.; Greenhood, Hugh; Greenwood, Isaac J. Jr.; Harris, Robert; Hayden, Horace E.; Heaton, Augustus G.; Hills, Jonas C.; James, Frederick H.; Johnes, Edward R.; Kennedy, John S.; Kirkwood, James; Lee, Francis B.; Lee, William; Lillard, John F.B.; Maris, Edward; Marvin, William T.R.; Massamore,George W.; McArthur, George; McLachlan, Robert W.; Morris, Charles; Parish, Daniel, Jr.; Pell, John; Perini, Quintilio; John H.; Pfund, Anthony; Pryer, Charles; Renwick, Edward L.; Richter, Max H.; Snowden, Archibald L.; Soverel, Herbert F.; Steers, Edward P.; Stehlin, Charles V.; Sterling, Edward B.; Stewart, William R.; Stickney, Matthew A.; Stone, Charles P; Strobridge, William H.; Tatman, Charles T.; Ten Eyck, James; Tuthill, Luther B.; Thruston, Gates P.; Tiemann, Edward L.; Trumbull, Walter; Vail, Joseph H.; Van Schaick, James; Warner, Thomas; Willis, Benjamin A.; White, John S.; Wood, Isaac F.; Wyckoff, Peter B. MD; Young, William H.
  The 19th century questionnaires are open to all researchers. Those from 1995 and 2002 are closed to outside researchers.
  - Box 1 of 2 (Shared with series “Publication Acknowledgments”)
    - Membership survey, 1889
    - Membership survey—Blanks, 1890s
    - Membership survey—Circular of members questionnaires, 1890s
    - Membership survey, 1995
  - Box 2 of 2: 2002 survey—Completed forms and draft report
- Series: Wills, bequests, gifts, and special funds records, 1912-ongoing; 4 cubic feet (3 boxes, 1 cabinet drawer)
  Users searching for coin donors and donations should also consult the following series in the Curatorial record group (RG2): (1) Coin Collection Accession Records by Accession Number and (2) Coin Collection Accession Records by Subject and Year.
  Users searching for cash and other donations should also consult the following series in the record group Development and Membership (RG3 [this record group]): Donation Files.
  Contains records mostly relating to funds and material donations received in the form of a bequest, but also to gifts and to the establishment and administering of special funds from living donors. Includes correspondence, wills and other legal documents, and occasionally lists of donated coin and library materials.
  Wills; Correspondence; Lists
  Closed to outside researchers.
  - Box 1 (letter size)
    - Avery Fund, 1912-1916
    - Avery Fund, 1913
    - Backowske, Michael Louis, Memorial Purchase Fund
    - Bass General Endowment Fund, 1975
    - Bass Library Fund, 1971
    - Beatty, William Gedney – Library, collection donation, fund establishment, 1941, 1949
    - Bequests – Possible and actual, 1954-1972
    - Betton, James L., estate of, 1998
    - Brunner, Emma B., 1940-1954
    - Clapp Fund and Collection, 1934-1936, 1995-2000
    - CNL, gift of, from the Colonial Newsletter Foundation, 1999-2006
    - Edlow Education Fund, 1992-1997
    - Gale, Brian O., Jr., Coin Purchase Fund, 1976
    - Ganz, David L. – Letter, excerpt from will, 1991
    - General Publication Fund, 1936
    - Greek Coin Purchase Fund, 1977
    - Groves, Donald, Fund, 1984
    - Hamad Al-Thani, Sheikh, Fund for Islamic Numismatics, 1995
    - Heaton, Charles, 1984-1987
    - Hersh, Charles, bequest, 2002
    - Lhotka, John and Mary, Memorial Coin Purchase Fund, 1960-1966
    - Memorial Decorations Fund – Also, Saltus Donation Fund, George L. Hamilton Collection, 1940-1951
    - Merritt Library Fund, 1924
    - Mildenberg, Leo, bequest, 2001
    - Newell, Edward T., Collection and Funds, 1941-1944
    - Newman, Eric P., Education Fund, 1981-1988
    - Pan American Resources, 1971, 1988-1989
    - Pessolano-Filos, Francis, 1987
    - Ray, Jessie Newby – Probate – Will, 1968
    - Raymond, Doris – Last will and testament, 1956, 1982
    - Raymond, Doris, estate, 1982
    - Risk, James C., 1998
    - Rothschild, Katharina, bequest, 1984
    - Saltus, J. Sanford – Medal fund, 1913
    - Schonwalter, Robert, 1998-1999
    - Schwartz, Francis M., Memorial Fund – Donors, 1985
    - Schwartz, Francis M., Memorial Fund – Donors, 1985
    - Schwartz, Francis M., Memorial Fund – Donors, 1985
    - Schwartz, Francis M., Memorial Fund, 2005
    - Scoville, Herbert, will, 1937-1938
    - Sullivan, George H., Memorial Fund, 1919-1929
    - Thompson, Margaret, Greek Chair Fund, 1986
    - Thompson, Margaret, will, 1986-1993
    - Thompson, Margaret, Memorial Lecture, 1996
    - United States Numismatics Chair, 1992
    - Weller, Michael J., trust, 2008
    - West, Louis C. – Last will and testament, 1927-1976
    - Williams, Charles K., II, 1973-1987
    - Fowler, Harry – Last will and testament, 1992
    - Groh, Mary – Last will and testament, 1909
  - Box 2 (legal size 1)
    - Burton Y. Berry – Agreement, 1961
    - Burton Y. Berry – Inventory
    - Burton Y. Berry – Coin photographs
    - Burton Y. Berry, 1960-1980
    - Burton Y. Berry, 1951-1959
    - Burton Y. Berry, 1959-1962
    - Burton Y. Berry, 1960
    - Burton Y. Berry, 1961
    - Burton Y. Berry, 1961-1962
    - Burton Y. Berry, 1964-1965
    - Burton Y. Berry, 1968-1980
    - Eidlitz, Robert J. – Will and Building Maintenance Fund, 1937-1961
    - Eidlitz, Robert J. – Correspondence – construction proceedings, Sadie Boulton Eidlitz settling accounts, 1956-1961
    - Eidlitz, Robert J. – Construction proceedings, 1956-1960
    - Eidlitz, Robert J. – Construction proceedings, 1959-1961
    - Eidlitz, Sadie Boulton – Settlement of account, 1957
    - Fecht, Arthur J., estate, 1980
    - Fecht Fund, 1948-1978
    - Fecht collection (1 of 2), 1943-1974
    - Fecht collection (2 of 2), 1981
    - Newell, Adra, 1950-1957, 1967
    - Newell, Adra, Bequest, 1967
    - Newell, Adra – Will, 1967
  - Box 3 (legal size 2)
    - Robinson, David M., bequest, 1957-1963
    - Robinson, David M., bequest, 1959-1960
    - Robinson, David M., estate of – Correspondence, 1957-1964
    - Robinson, David M., estate of, deceased, 1960
    - Rogasner, J. Donald, 1960
    - Rogasner, J. Donald – Coin collection, 1959-1960
    - Rogasner, J. Donald – Bequest, 1969-1985
    - Rogasner, J. Donald – Bequest, 1960, 1971-1972
    - Rogasner, J. Donald – Bequest, 1982, 1985
    - Solomon, Raphael, 1993-1995
  - Office Cabinet Drawer
    - Huntington Free Library – Book Purchase Fund, 1956-1999
    - Huntington Free Library, 1954-1955, 1975
    - Huntington Free Library – Litigation, 1997-2003
    - Huntington Free Library – Legal documents, 1954-1959
    - Huntington, Anna Hyatt, will of, 1927, 1974-1975
    - Huntington, Arabella D., Trust for A.M. Huntington, 1923, 1956
    - Huntington, Archer M., Charitable Trust B (established 1936), 1936-1987
    - Huntington, Archer M., Trust 1518 – Under indenture dated April 4, 1914 (1 of 2), 1914, 1942-1949
    - Huntington, Archer M., Trust 1518 – Under indenture dated April 4, 1914 (2 of 2), 1949-1996
    - Huntington, Archer M.—Donation, 1927
    - Huntington, Archer M., Trust (established 1927; dissolved 1995), 1947-1995
    - Huntington, Archer M., Trust, 2006
    - Huntington Numismatic Notes and Monographs Fund/General Publication Fund (established 1920), 1920, 1948-1972
    - Adams, Lawrence – Charitable Remainder Trust, 2011
    - Korein, Julius, estate, 2008-2009
    - Lhotka, John Francis, bequest, 2007-2008
    - Minners, Howard A. – Proposal for a Fund – Center for European and Renaissance Numismatics, 2011
    - Pike, Joseph E., estate of, 2009
    - Salton, Lottie, bequest, 2009
    - Salton, Mark M. – Annual Lecture Fund (established 2006), 2006-2011
    - Scher, Stephen K., Lecture, 1995-1996
    - Stack Family COAC (Coinage of the Americas) Fund, 2005
    - Wills and estates – Lawyers, 2004
- Series: Donation files, 1894-1999, bulk 1951-1999; 13.5 cubic feet (14 boxes)
  Users searching for cash and other donations should also consult the following series in this record group (Development and Membership, RG3): Wills, Bequests, Gifts, and Special Funds Records.
  Correspondence; Lists (Document genres); Notes; Photographs
  Contains records pertaining to gifts given by donors over time. Includes handwritten ledger pages, and later computer printouts, listing donor name along with coin, library, and cash donations with total monetary value; copies of outgoing acknowledgment letters with account numbers; and occasionally letters, appraisal documents, signed unrestricted gift forms, notes, membership dues cards, lists of coins donated, and coin photographs.
  This series consists of two sets of files arranged by name from A to Z. It is not apparent why the sets were kept separately, since the two overlap in both time span and content. Users should consult both sets when looking for a donor name.
- Series: ANS Magazine production compact discs, 2003-2004, 2006-2010, 0.3 cubic feet (1 box)
  Most images also in Magazine directories on the main server.
  Compact discs
  Compact discs with images and publisher files used in the creation of ANS Magazine, 2003-2004, 2006-2010.
- Series: Miscellaneous development and membership records, 1866 - 1989; 1 cubic foot (2 boxes and 2 oversized bound items)
  Correspondence; Notebooks; Circulars (Fliers); Lists; Levick, Joseph N.T. (Joseph Nepoleon Tricot), 1828-1908; Robertson, Robert, 1869-1937; Logs (Records)
  Various materials relating to the Society’s publications, membership, and fundraising, including the purchase and distribution of medals and publications and records of publications sent to members. Includes Joseph N.T. Levick’s annotated copy of the first volume of the American Journal of Numismatics (AJN) (1866), along with the original circular announcing the publication’s debut (pasted in) and accounts and lists relating to coin purchases either for him personally or for the Society. (It was Levick who first proposed the publication of AJN and he served as its first editor.) Also of note is correspondence relating to the purchase and distribution of Albert Frey’s Dictionary of Numismatic Names (1917-1918); correspondence regarding the efforts to raise funds to purchase the Swedish coin collection of Robert Robertson (1929.103), and subscription forms and letters for the School for Coin and Medal Designing and Die Cutting and for two of the Society’s earliest medals: Membership (1875-1880) Charles E. Anthon (1884).
  A log book listing members that purchased various medals (1909-1986) is also included. With varying completeness, it lists number of metal type struck, artist, subscriber name, address, metal, date of payment, amount, date of shipment, and method of shipment. Medals included are Hudson-Fulton; Catholic, or Archdiocese of New York; Cleveland; Members; Babelon; Morgan; Lincoln Plaque; New Theatre; Declaration of War; Catskill Aqueduct; French and British War Commission; Belgian; Joan of Arc; Independence Day; Peace; Prince of Wales; Red Cross; Foch; Choate; Washington; Members; 125th Anniversary; and Statue of Liberty. An envelope of circulars for many of the medals is included with the book.
  Two files of membership data are closed to outside researchers. The rest of the materials are open.
  - Box 1 of 4
    - American Journal of Numismatics—vol. 1—Annotated and with additional material—Levick, 1866 (2 folders)
    - Charles E. Anthon medals—Completed subscription forms, 1884
    - Letters and completed forms requesting the Society’s Membership Medal (pasted into bound volume with Member’s Medal Honorary on spine), 1875-1880
    - List of members and tally of publications sent (bound volume), 1878-1886
    - American Journal of Numismatics (AJN)—Accounts, 1906-1909
    - ANS Centennial tickets—List of members (bound volume), April 1958
  - Box 2 of 4
    - School for Die Cutting—Completed subscription pledge forms, 1900
    - ANS Proceedings—Galley proofs, 1907
    - Dictionary of Numismatic Names—Albert R. Frey—Correspondence on purchasing and distributing, 1917-1918
    - Publications of the ANS—Letter and list, 1920
    - ANS medals wanted by members—Lists, 1920s
    - Indian peace medals purchase fundraising letter, n.d.
    - Robert Robertson Swedish coin collection (1929.103)—Fundraising correspondence, 1928
    - Membership roll, along with promotional information from Hapgoods of New York City, a national organization of employment experts, n.d.
    - Membership data, 1917-1957
    - Membership data—Payments A/R, 1980-1988
  - 3 of 4
    - Oversized notebook: List of members and tally of publications sent, 1921-1924 (loose)
  - 4 of 4
    - Medals log book, 1909-1986 (loose)
      An envelope of circulars for the medals that was kept with the log book can now be found in Box 2 of this series.